Now we'll look at insertion sort,
이제 우리는 흥미롭게도 선택 정렬과
which is another elementary method that interestingly has quite
성능 특성이 상당히 다른 또다른
different performance characteristics than selection sort.
기본 방법인 삽입 정렬을 살펴보겠습니다.
Let's look at a demo of insertion sort.
삽입 정렬의 데모를 살펴보겠습니다.
For insertion sort, what we're going to do is we'll move an index i
삽입 정렬의 경우, 우리가 할 것은 우리는 이전처럼 색인 i를
from left to right as before, but now, in the i'th iteration,
왼쪽에서 오른쪽으로 이동할 것이지만, 하지만 지금은, i번째 반복문에서,
we're going to move a[i] into position among the elements to its left.
우리는 a[i]를 그것의 왼쪽에 있는 원소 사이의 위치로 이동할 것입니다.
Let's look at how that works on our example with cards.
카드로 우리의 사례가 어떻게 작동하는지 보겠습니다.
So, now we start by initializing i at the first card, and
그럼, 이제 우리는 첫번째 카드에 i를 초기화하는 것으로 시작하고,
we take the idea that everything from i to its left is going to be sorted, and
기본적인 아이디어는 i 왼쪽은 정렬될 것이고,
everything from the right we're not going to look at at all.
오른쪽에서의 모든 것을 우리는 살펴보지 않을 것입니다.
So everything to the left of i is in ascending order, everything to the right,
그래서 i의 왼쪽에 있는 모든것은 오름 차순으로 정리되어 있고, 오른쪽에 있는 모든 것들은,
we haven't seen it all yet.
우리는 아직 전혀 본 적이 없습니다.
So now when we increment i, well, in this case it's already in order,
그럼 이제 우리가 i를 늘릴 때, 음, 이 경우에는 이미 순서대로 정렬이 되어있어서
we don't have anything else to do.
우리는 더이상 할 일이 없습니다.
In the third case now, when i is at the third entry in the array,
세번째 경우에 이제, i가 배열에서 세번째 항목일 때,
now we start a index j, and we move that starting at i to the left.
이제 우리는 색인 j에서 시작합니다, 그리고 우리는 i에서 시작하여 왼쪽으로 이동합니다.
And what we need to do is just exchange the 5 with every element to its left
그리고 우리가 해야할 일은 단지 5를 왼쪽에 있는 더 큰 원소들과
that's greater.
교환하는 것입니다.
So first we exchange it with the 10, it's still not in place, so
그래서 처음에 우리는 10과 교환했고, 아직 제자리에 없어서,
we exchange it with the 7.
우리는 7과 교환합니다.
Now we get to the beginning of the array, and once we've done that or
이제 우리는 배열의 시작에 도달하고, 일단 그렇게 하거나
we've hit a smaller element, then we have everybody to the left of i in order.
우리가 더 작은 원소에 닿으면, 우리는 i의 왼쪽에 있는 모두를 순서대로 배열하게 된겁니다
So now we increment that again, and we come to the 3.
그럼 이제 우리는 인덱스 i를 1 증가시켜서, 우린 3으로 넘어가보죠.
Again, we exchange as long as the card immediately to the left is greater.
다시말해, 우리는 바로 왼쪽에 있는 카드가 더 큰 한 즉시 교환합니다.
And once we've done that,
그리고 우리가 이렇게 하고나면,
then we have everything to the left by in ascending order.
우리는 왼쪽 값 모두를 오름차순으로 정렬합니다
Now, in this case, we have the 8, and we only have to exchange one, and
이제, 이 경우에, 우리는 8이 있고, 그리고 우리는 단 1개만 교환해야하고,
now it's got the 7 to its left and everything is in order.
이제 7을 왼쪽에 두고 모두를 순서대로 있습니다.
So we've achieved putting it in order with less work in this case.
그래서 우리는 이 경우에 일을 덜 하면서 정돈해낼 수 있었습니다.
We don't always have to go all the way back to the beginning.
우리는 항상 처음으로 거슬러 갈 필요는 없습니다.
4, exchange it with everybody to its left that's greater,
4는, 우리가 더 작은 원소를 찾을 때까지 그보다 더 큰 왼쪽에서 모두와 교환하고나서,
until we find a smaller element, then it's in ascending order.
오름차순으로 정렬합니다.
2 has to go all the way back to the beginning.
2는 배열의 처음까지 도달해야 되겠네요.
But then the very next one, the 9 has to only go back one position,
하지만 바로 다음에, 9는 오직 한번만 이동하면되고,
and the 6 has to go about halfway back.
6은 반 정도만 돌아가야 합니다.
And then we have the entire array sorted.
그리고 나서 우리는 전체 배열을 분류했습니다.
Again, we can look at insertion sort in terms of invariants.
다시, 우리는 불변 면에서 삽입정렬을 살보볼 수 있습니다.
Our pointer still scans from left to right, but
우리의 포인터는 여전히 왼쪽에서 오른쪽으로 스캔하지만,
now the elements to the left of the pointer, including it,
이제 포인터의 왼쪽에 있는 원소들은, 그것을 포함해서,
are in order, but the elements to the right have not yet been seen at all.
순서대로지만, 오른쪽 원소들은 아직 전혀 보이지 않았습니다.
So we have to look at the code that's going to maintain that invariant as
그래서 우리는 포인터가 증가함에 따라 불변하는 상태를 유지하는 코드를
the pointer increments.
살펴보아야 합니다.
Move the pointer to the right, it's incremented again.
포인터를 오른쪽으로 움직이면, 다시 증가합니다.
Now the invariant's broken because the element on
포인터의 성분이 정렬되지 않아서
the pointer is not in sorted order.
이제 불변은 부서졌습니다.
To put it in sorted order, we have to move from right to left, exchanging it with
잘 정돈하기 위해서, 우리는 오른쪽에서 왼쪽으로 이동해야하고, 왼쪽값이 클 때마다 항상
every larger elements to its left, and that's what the code at the bottom does.
왼쪽값과 교환하고, 그것이 밑에 있는 코드가 하는 것입니다.
It starts j at i, and decrements j,
i에서 시작하는 j로 시작하고, j의 감소,
exchanging j with the elements to its left,
그 왼쪽 요소들과 j를 교환하고,
a of j with the element to its left, a of j-1,
a[j]를 a[j-1]과 교환합니다
as long as a of j is less than a of j-1 or j is bigger than 0.
a[j]가 a[j-1]보다 작다면 말이죠
And that immediately gives this code for insertion sort,
그리고 그것은 즉시 삽입 정렬에 이 코드를 주는데,
which is similar to our code for selection sort and just as simple.
이것은 우리의 선택정렬 코드와 유사하고 간단합니다.
It's got two nested for loops, selection sort had two nested for loops,
중첩된 두개의 루프가 있는데, 선택정렬은 두개의 중첩된 루프,
a test, a comparison, and an exchange inside the for loop.
테스트, 비교, 그리고 루프의 내부 교환이 있습니다.
And that's a fine implementation of an elementary sorting method.
그리고 그것은 기본적인 분류 방법의 좋은 실행입니다.
What about the analysis of insertion sort?
삽입 정렬의 분석은 어떻게 할까요?
It's more complicated.
더욱 복잡합니다.
Our proposition says that insertion sort, to sort randomly ordered array
우리의 명제는 무작위로 정돈된 배열을 분류하는 삽입정렬은,
with distinct keys, it'll use about one quarter N squared compares,
그것은 약 1/4 N제곱을 비교하고,
and about the same number, one quarter N squared exchanges, on the average.
그리고 거의 같은 숫자로, 평균적으로, 1/4 N제곱을 교환합니다.
This is more complicated to prove.
이것은 증명하기 더 복잡합니다.
It depends on the array being randomly ordered.
임의로 정돈하는 배열에 따라 다릅니다.
And again, you can get a feeling for
그리고 다시, 여러분은 이 N을 N추적을
where the proposition comes from by looking at this N by N trace.
살펴봄으로써 나오는 제안이 나오는 느낌의 형태를 얻을 수 있습니다.
Again, the black elements are the ones that we compare, and
다시말해, 우리가 비교하는 것은 블랙 요소들이고,
actually, they're also the exchanges.
교환도 검은 값들에서 이루어집니다.
On the red one is the one that's finally put into place.
빨간색 위에 있는 것은 마지막으로 자리 잡은 것입니다.
And you can see that for a large array that's randomly ordered, the element
그리고 여러분은 무작위로 정돈된 큰 배열에서는,
that we put into place is going to go about halfway back on the average.
평균 절반정도 되돌아 가야합니다.
So that means about half the elements below the diagonal are going to be black
즉 대각선 아래에 있는 요소의 절반 정도가 평균적으로 검정색이
on the average.
된다는 의미입니다.
There's N squared over 2 below the diagonal,
대각선 아래에 N 제곱 나누기 2가 있고,
half of that is N squared over 4.
절반은 N 제곱 나누기 4입니다.
The exact analysis is not much more detailed than that.
정확한 분석은 그보다 훨씬 더 상세하지는 않습니다.
This is a bigger trace that shows, again,
이것은 더 큰 추적을 보여주고, 다시,
about half the elements below the diagonal are involved in the sort.
대각선 아래의 절반 정도의 요소들이 이 종류에 속합니다.
[COUGH] Let's look at an animation.
[기침] 애니메이션을 봐봅시다.
Since N squared over 4 versus N squared over 2,
N제곱 나누기 2에 비해 N제곱 나누기 4부터,
insertion sort's going to be about twice as fast as selection sort.
삽입정렬은 선택정렬보다 두배 정도 빠를 것입니다.
So we can do about twice as many items in the trace in the same amount of time.
그래서 우리는 추적을 하면 동일한 시간에 두배 정도 되는 항목만큼 할 수 있습니다.
It grabs an element and brings it back into position every time.
그것은 요소를 잡아서 매번 제자리로 다시 갖다 놓습니다.
So that's an animation for randomly ordered items.
그래서 이것은 무작위로 정돈된 항목을 위한 영상이죠.
Now, insertion sort does depend on the initial order of the data.
이제, 삽입정렬은 데이터의 초기 순서에 따라 달라집니다.
Let's look at the best case and the worst case, which are certainly outliers.
확실히 분리된, 가장 좋은 경우와 가장 나쁜 경우를 봅시다.
If the array happens to be already sorted, all insertion sort
만약 배열이 이미 정렬되었다면, 모든 삽입정렬은
does is really validate that each element has got smaller elements to its left.
각 요소들이 그들의 왼쪽에 더 작은 요소가 있음을 실제로 확인하는 것입니다.
So it does no exchanges.
그래서 교환하지 않습니다.
It gets the sorting job done with just N minus 1 compares.
정렬 작업 완료는 N 빼기 1에 필적합니다.
On the other hand, if the array is in descending order and
반면에, 만약 배열이 내림차순이고
has no duplicates, then every element goes all the way back.
중복이 없다면, 모든 요소들은 되돌아 갑니다.
It makes n squared over 2 compares and n squared over 2 exchanges.
n제곱 나누기 2를 필적하고 n제곱 나누기 2를 교환합니다.
So in the first case, it's much,
그래서 첫번째 경우에는, 그것은,
much faster than selection sort, linear instead of quadratic.
이차함수가 선형이기때문에, 선택정렬보다 훨씬, 훨씬 빠릅니다.
In the second case, it's slower than selection sort,
두번째 경우에는, 선택정렬보다 느린데,
because it uses about the same number of compares, but it uses many more exchanges.
왜냐하면 같은 수의 비교를 사용하지만, 더 많은 교환을 사용하기 때문입니다.
So let's see that in the animation.
자 그럼 영상에서 확인해봅시다.
So this is when the items come in in reverse order.
자 여기 항목들이 역순으로 옵니다.
Now, every time it gets a new item,
이제, 새로운 항목을 받을 때마다,
it has to exchange it all the way back to the beginning.
그것은 처음으로 되돌아가 교환해야합니다.
Same kind of dynamic characteristic as selection sort, except, for
선택정렬과 같은 종류의 동적 특성이죠, 단지,모든 단계를,
every step, it's not just comparing,
단순히 비교하는게 아니라,
it's also exchanging, which makes it even slower in practice.
서로 교환도 하기 때문에 실제로는 더욱 느립니다.
So this is a bad case that we wouldn't like to see in a practical application.
따라서 이것은 우리가 실제 어플리케이션에서 보고 싶지 않은 나쁜 경우입니다.
But there's also a good case that actually we take advantage of in plenty of
하지만 실제로 우리는 많은 실제 어플리케이션에서 활용하는 좋은 경우
practical applications.
또한 있습니다.
And that has to do with when the array is partially sorted.
그리고 배열이 부분적으로 정렬되어 있을 때 해야합니다.
To talk about this in a quantitative way, we define what's called an inversion.
양적인 방법으로 이것에 대해 이야기 하기 위해, 우리는 역위라 불리는 것을 정의합니다.
An inversion is just a pair of keys that are out of order in the array.
역위는 단지 배열에서 잘못된 일련의 키입니다.
So this array has six inversions, T and
그래서 이 배열은 6개의 역위가 있고, R이 T보다 먼저 가야하기 때문에,
R are out of order, because R should go before T.
T와 R은 잘못되었습니다.
T and P are out of order, and so forth.
T와 P는 잘못되었습니다.
This array has six inversions.
이 배열은 6개의 역위가 있습니다.
And we define an array to be partially sorted if its number of
그리고 만약 역외 횟수가 선형이라면, 일정 정수 곱하기 N보다 작다면,
inversions is linear, if it's less than some constant times N.
우리는 배열이 부분적으로 정렬되었다고 정의합니다.
And partially sorted arrays appear often in practice.
그리고 부분적으로 정렬된 배열은 실제로 종종 나타납니다.
For example, if you have a large array with just a few, that's sorted except for
예를 들어, 만약 여러분이 큰 배열이 있는데
just a few unsorted elements appended at the end,
마지막에 덧붙인 몇개의 정렬되지 않은 요소만 있다면, 그것은
it's going to be partially sorted.
부분적으로 정렬될 것입니다.
Or in other cases, if you only have a few entries out of place,
또는 다른 경우에는, 만약 여러분이 단지 몇개의 잘못된 항목이 있다면,
the array's going to be partially sorted.
배열은 부분적으로 정렬될 것입니다.
These types of things arise often in practical applications.
이런 종류의 일들은 실제 어플리케이션에서 종종 발생합니다.
And what's interesting about insertion sort is that it runs in linear time for
그리고 삽입정렬에서 흥미로운 것은 부분적으로 정렬된 배열에 대해
partially sorted arrays.
선형으로 실행됩니다.
And the proof is, the number of comparisons and the number of exchanges is
그리고 그 증거는, 비교의 수와 교환의 수는
equal to the number of exchanges equal to the number of inversions, and
교환의 수와 같고 역위의 수와 같고,
there's an extra compare for every element except the first.
첫번째를 제외하고는 모든 요소에 대해 추가적인 비교가 있습니다.
So let's look at how that looks in the animation.
그럼 어떻게 보이는지 영상으로 살펴봅시다.
Here's a partially sorted array, and
여기 부분적으로 정렬된 배열이 있고,
you can see that insertion sort quickly gets the job done.
여러분은 삽입정렬이 빠르게 완료되는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
We're going to take advantage of this a little bit later in this lecture.
우리는 이 강의에서 조금 더 뒤에 이것을 활용할 것입니다.
That's insertion sort, our second elementary sorting method.
여기까지 우리의 두번째 요소 정렬 방법인, 삽입정렬입니다.